Guide to the Health Systems Agency of Southwestern Pennsylvania Records, 1971-1987 AIS.1987.02
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Health Systems Agency of Southwestern Pennsylvania Records
1971-1987
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Health Systems Agency of Southwestern Pennsylvania
AIS.1987.02
180.75 Linear Feet (145 boxes)
The Health Systems Agency of Southwestern Pennsylvania was a health care industry coordinating organization, administered by a board made up of both health professionals and political figures. While little is known about the agency, it is clear from the records that it had a hand in directing the expansion of the health care industry in the greater Pittsburgh region during the three decades between 1960 and 1990.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Health Systems Agency of Southwestern Pennsylvania in 1987.
Related Material
Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County, Pittsburgh, Pa., Records 1943-1950, AIS.1968.14a, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Montefiore Hospital Records, 1905-1976, AIS.1981.14, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Visiting Nurse Association of Allegheny County Records, Inc., 1918-2000, AIS.2000.13, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
History
The Health Systems Agency of Southwestern Pennsylvania was formed during the 1960's as a coordinating body for the expanding health care industry in the greater Pittsburgh region. Officials related to the agency included health care professionals, the foundation community, and political figures. The agency worked in concert with other health care associations, including the Comprehensive Health Planning Association of Western Pennsylvania and the Hospital Planning Association. Little details are known about the mission and objectives of the organization at this time. However, by 1971 this agency became responsible for the distribution of federal funding to expand and update health care facilities and programs at hospitals, neighborhood clinics, and nursing care centers throughout southwestern Pennsylvania. Documentation on the projects that were funded through this program are the only records that are currently available for researchers to access. Each funded project has a unique identification number, beginning with number 1 and ending with project number 1601. The projects include: construction projects, purchase of new equipment, implementation of new programs, and updates to building infrastructure. The funding of projects and the demise of the Health System Agency ends in 1987.
Previous Citation
Health Systems Agency of Southwestern Pennsylvania Records, 1971-1987, AIS.1987.02, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Scope and Content Notes
Included in the records are case files for the 1601 funded projects coordinated by the Health Systems Agency of Southwestern Pennsylvania dating from 1971 to 1987. Each funded project is identified numarically, 1 thru 1601. The folder headings indicate the project number, the institution recieving the funding, and the name of the project. Project files include correspondence, proposals, financial statements, and periodic reports. A project file can consist of a single file folder of documentation or for larger project mutliple file folders.
The case files for the funded projects are the only series currently available for research. Due to the size and complexity of the entire collection of records, additional record series will be processed at a future date. Other record series will include board of directors minutes and various administrative files of the Health Systems Agency.
Health services administration -- Pennsylvania, Southwestern; Health facilities -- Pennsylvania, Southwestern; Associations; Health and medicine; Health systems agencies -- Pennsylvania, Southwestern; Clinical medicine -- Pennsylvania, Southwestern; Nursing homes -- Pennsylvania, Southwestern; Hospitals -- Pennsylvania, Southwestern; Medical care -- Pennsylvania, Southwestern; Regional medical programs -- Pennsylvania, Southwestern; Public health administration -- Pennsylvania, Southwestern; Health Systems Agency of Southwestern Pennsylvania
- Projects, 1971-1987; I.
  - 1-Allegheny General Hospital--Renovation, 1971 (Box 90)
  - 2-Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh--Standby Generator, 1971
  - 3-Mercy Hospital of Pittsburgh--Construction, Renovation, Bed Replacement & Siregraph Equipment Replacement, 1971
  - 4-PA State Planning Board W.P.--Planning prospectus of the Ellwood City Hospitals, appendix of regional planning and development activities, 1971
  - 5-Ellwood City Hospital--Construction of new hospital, 1972
  - 6-Manchester Health Center--Construction of the Manchester Health Center, 1972
  - 7-Westmoreland Manor--beds, the acquisition of two nursing homes, and the replacement of the Manor's older building, 1971
  - 8-Renal Disease Program--Western PA renal disease program, 1971
  - 9-United-Rochester Hospitals--Merger of the United and the Rochester General Hospitals, building of a new hospital, 1971
  - 10-Greene County Memorial Hospital--Modernization and Construction, 1971
  - 11-Uniontown Hospital--Phase I construction of emergency and outpatient departments, 1972
  - 12-St. Johns General Hospital--Construction of Fleming Shelter, 1972
  - 13-Western Pennsylvania Hospital--six bed renal unit, 1973
  - 14-not present
  - 15-Community Health Association of Western Pennsylvania, 1971
  - 16-Jeanette District Memorial Hospital--Modifications to second floor, 1972
  - 17-not present
  - 18-not present
  - 19-not present
  - 20-Western Pennsylvania Regional Medical Program--program in diabetes, obesity and endocrine disorders, 1971
  - 21-Western Pennsylvania Regional Medical Program--sickle cell anemia and related hemoglobinopathies, 1971
  - 22-Western Pennsylvania Regional Medical Program--Evaluation of emergency resuscitation/implementation of education programs in cardiopulmonary resuscitation, 1971
  - 23-Department of Health, Education, and Welfare--Proposal for a Neighborhood Improvement-Rodent Control Program for the Turtle Creek Valley Model Cities, 1971
  - 24-Horizon Home--Application for the construction of Horizon Home, 1971
  - 25-not present
  - 26-not present
  - 27-Western Pennsylvania Regional Medical Program--Hypertension Management Program, 1971
  - 28-Western Pennsylvania Regional Medical Program--Beaver County Heart Association Lipid Screening Project, 1973
  - 29-Empty File
  - 30-Western Pennsylvania Regional Medical Program--Program for the preparation, demonstration and evaluation of primary care nurse practitioners, 1971
  - 31-Western Pennsylvania Regional Medical Program--Regionalized program in radiation therapy, 1971
  - 32-Central Medical Pavilion--Construction of Central Medical Pavilion, 1972 (Box 91)
  - 33-Greene County Emergency and Welfare Service--"Parish House", 1971
  - 34-not present
  - 35-Stanley Whitehall Sheltered Workshop--Proposal for construction of the Stanley Whitehall Sheltered Workshop, Undated
  - 36-Evergreen Convalescent Home--Construction of addition to house skilled beds, 1972
  - 37-University Health Center of Pittsburgh--Bridge connecting Presbyterian-University Hospital and Western Psychiatric Institute and Clinic, 1972
  - 38-Hazelwood Health Council--Request for employment, 1972
  - 39-Presbyterian-University Hospital--Drug Treatment Program, Undated
  - 40-New Kensington Miners' Clinic--Alle-Kiski Family Planning Program, 1972
  - 41-Allegheny County Health Department--Application for the continuation of the Allegheny County Rodent Control Project, 1972
  - 42-Pennsylvania Medical Society--Medical Care Appraisal Project, 1972
  - 43-Allegheny County Health Department--Immunization Project, 1972
  - 44-Westmoreland Hospital--Pediatric Dental Service Project, 1972
  - 45-Monsour Medical Foundation--HMO planning grant, 1972
  - 46-St. John's Lutheran Home--112 bed addition, 1972 (Box 92)
  - 47-University Health Center of Pittsburgh--Health maintenance organization, 1972
  - 48-St. Francis General Hospital--Modernization of North Wing, 1972
  - 49-Monsour Hospital--Adult dental program, 1972
  - 50-not present
  - 51-Pennsylvania Department of Health--Venereal disease control, 1972
  - 52-Department of Public Welfare--Venereal disease and Rubella control, 1972
  - 53-Empty File
  - 54-Westmoreland Hospital--Radiation Facility, 1972
  - 55-Allegheny County Health Department--Lead Poisoning Control Program
  - 56-Jeannette District Memorial Hospital--Construction and Renovation, 1971
  - 57-not present
  - 58-Allegheny County Health Department--Public health center, 1972
  - 59-Sunnyview Home of Butler--Addition of beds, 1973
  - 60-Allegheny Council on Emergency Medical Services--Helicopter proposal, 1972
  - 61-Family Planning Council of Southwestern Pennsylvania--Second year continuation grant, 1972
  - 62-Monsour Hospital--Radiation Therapy Unit, 1972
  - 63-United Family Services of Pittsburgh--Family health centers, 1972
  - 64-not present
  - 65-Allegheny County Council on Emergency Medical and Health Services--Area wide emergency medical care system, 1972
  - 66-Western Pennsylvania Regional Medical Program--Consumer Health Information and Education Federation Project Proposal, 1972
  - 67-not present
  - 68-not present
  - 69-Community Care Clinic of Northwest Washington County--National Health Service Corps personnel, 1973
  - 70-Westmoreland County Community College Associate Degree Nursing Program--Establishment of program, 1972
  - 71-Citizens General Hospital--Air conditioning unit, 1972
  - 72-Indiana YMCA--Drug Helpline, 1972
  - 73-Monongahela Memorial Hospital--Acute Care Facility, 1972
  - 74-Overlook Medical Clinic--Addition, 1972 (Box 93)
  - 75-McKeesport Hospital--Construction of a wing, 1972
  - 76-Henry Clay Frick Hospital--Emergency room and outpatient department expansion, 1972
  - 77-Pittsburgh Free Medical Clinic--Proposal to open up day-time primary health care, 1972
  - 78-Allegheny Valley Hospital--First & second annual reports/Additions, 1973
  - 79-The Pennsylvania State Plan for Hospital and Medical Facilities--1972 Amendments
  - 80-Fayette County Development Council--Fayette Community Health Service Center, 1972
  - 81-Mercy Hospital--Addition of a corp. physician, 1973
  - 82-Homewood-Brushton Neighborhood Health Center--Refunding Request, 1973
  - 83-Latrobe Area Hospital--Ambulatory Care Center, 1972
  - 84-Homewood-Brushton Neighborhood Health Center--Drug Rehabilitation Program, 1972
  - 85-Westmoreland County Council on Alcoholism--AA-oriented, transitional living program, 1972
  - 86-Butler County Community College--Associate Degree Career Ladder Nursing Education Program, 1972
  - 87-Butler County Memorial Hospital--Renovation of Radiology Department, 1974
  - 88-Westmoreland Hospital Association--Super voltage radiation therapy facility proposal, 1972
  - 89-Family Planning Advisory Committee--Establishment of family planning service in Butler County, 1973
  - 90-Community Health Association of Western Pennsylvania--Continuation of funds, 1972
  - 91-St. Francis General Hospital--Modernization, 1974 (Box 94)
  - 92-Grandview Extendicare--New facility in New Castle, 1972
  - 93-Divine Providence Hospital--Renovation and expansion proposal, 1972
  - 94-Jameson Memorial Hospital—Super voltage radiation therapy, 1973
  - 95-Western Pennsylvania Regional Medical Program--Program to teach registered nurses to screen for cervical cancer, 1973
  - 96-Western Pennsylvania Regional Medical Program--Biochemical screening and diagnostic test for early detection of genital malignancy, 1973
  - 97-Western Pennsylvania Regional Medical Program--Education of nurses in adult ambulatory care, 1973
  - 98-Western Pennsylvania Regional Medical Program--A comprehensive chronic renal care system for Western Pennsylvania, 1973
  - 99-St. John's Lutheran Home-- Construction of 175-bed addition, 1973
  - 100-Lutheran Welfare Concordia Home--Proposal for expansion, 1979
  - 101-Western Pennsylvania Regional Medical Program--Regional Neonatal Program, 1973
  - 102-Western Pennsylvania Regional Medical Program--Arlington Heights/St. Clair Village Primary Care Demonstration, 1973
  - 103-not present
  - 104-Western Pennsylvania Regional Medical Program--Emergency Medical Services Training Project, 1973
  - 105-Allegheny Valley Mental Health and Mental Retardation Center--Ten bed in-patient psychiatric unit at Citizens General Hospital, 1973
  - 106-Western Pennsylvania Regional Medical Program--Develop a curriculum to educate health professionals in the principles and techniques of the health education process, 1973
  - 107- Centralized Hospital Services of Southwestern Pennsylvania--Central laundry facility, 1973 (Box 95)
  - 108-Easter Seal Society--Establishment grant application for Easter Seal Workshop, 1973
  - 109-Allegheny County Health Department--Rodent Control Program, 1973
  - 110-South Hills Health System--Refinancing, 1974
  - 111-Johns Hopkins University--Experimental Medical Care Review Organization, 1973
  - 112-Homewood-Brushton Neighborhood Health Center--Manpower request under the National Health Service Corps Program, 1973
  - 113-St. Clair Memorial Hospital--First Annual Report, 1973
  - 114-Sewickley Valley Hospital--Long Range Development Program, 1973 (Box 96)
  - 115-Community Medical Center of Northwest Washington County--National Health Services Corps, 1973
  - 116-St. Francis General Hospital--Annual Reports, 1975
  - 117-Pennsylvania Association for the Blind (Pittsburgh Branch)--Construction and Renovation
  - 118-East Suburban General Hospital--Establishment proposal, 1973 (Box 97)
  - 119-Carmichaels Clinic--Manpower request under the National Health Service Corps Program, 1973
  - 120-The West Haven Nursing Home--Construction of building
  - 121-Columbia Hospital--Forbes Hospital System long range plan, 1973
  - 122-Westmoreland Hospital Association--Super voltage Radiation Therapy Facility, 1974
  - 123-Westmoreland Hospital Association--Home Health Care Proposal, 1973
  - 124-not present
  - 125-Family Planning Council of Southwestern Pennsylvania--Application For Continuation Grant (Third Year), 1973
  - 126-Aliquippa Hospital--Development Proposals, 1973
  - 127-not present
  - 128-Allegheny County Health Department--Immunization Project, 1973
  - 129-not present
  - 130-Pennsylvania Department of Health--Continuation Application for Communicable Disease Control in Pennsylvania, 1973
  - 131-Sugar Creek Rest Intermediate Care Facility--Plan For Construction of Facility, 1973
  - 132-Allegheny County Health Department--Childhood Lead Poisoning Proposal, 1973
  - 133-Fair Winds Manor Nursing Home--Renovate and Replace 18 Beds, 1973
  - 134-Cambria County Home and Hospitals--First, Second and Third Annual Reports, 1974 (Box 98)
  - 135-St. Clair Memorial Hospital--Replacement of Equipment, 1974
  - 136-not present
  - 137-not present
  - 138-North Hills Passavant Hospital-Outpatient Surgical Facility, 1975
  - 139-St. Johns General Hospital--Application For Construction of Alcoholism and Drug Rehabilitation Center, 1973
  - 140-Shadyside Hospital--Replacement of Blood Analysis Equipment, 1975
  - 141-Homestead Hospital--Continuation Grant for Mental Health Center, 1973
  - 142-Washington County Long Term Care Facility--First, Second, 1974
  - 143-Latrobe Area Hospital--Mental Health Center Federal Staffing Grant, 1973
  - 144- CARCOA--Proposal for Gerontology Center and Nursing Home Facility, 1973
  - 145-Allegheny General Hospital--Continuation of Incremental Dental Health Care Program, 1973
  - 146-South Hills Health System--Homestead Hospital Special Procedures Radiology Unit, 1975
  - 147-Jeannette District Memorial Hospital--Personal Health Services Proposal, 1974
  - 148-Medical Center of Beaver County--Sale of Rochester Unit, Replacement of Three Hospitals With One Facility, 1976 (Box 99)
  - 149-Beaver County Hospital--Addition of 99 Intermediate Beds, 1974
  - 150-State Department of Health--Proposal for Demonstration Nutrition Project, 1975
  - 151-Kade Nursing Home- First and Second Annual Reports, 1974
  - 152-Westmoreland Hospital Association--Home Health Care Proposal, 1974
  - 153- Homewood-Brushton Neighborhood Health Center--Continuation Application, 1974 (Box 100)
  - 154-not present
  - 155-Westmoreland Hospital Association--Primary Care Center Relocation, 1975
  - 156-H.C. Frick Community Hospital--First Annual Report, 1974
  - 157-not present
  - 158-not present
  - 159-not present
  - 160-not present
  - 161-Medical Center of Beaver County--Beaver County Heart Association Lipid Screening Program, 1973
  - 162-University of Pittsburgh--Emergency Medical Services Training Program, 1973
  - 163-Presbyterian University Hospital--Cervical Cancer Screening Training for Registered Nurses, 1973
  - 164-University of Pittsburgh School of Nursing-- Adult Nurse Practitioner Training Program, 1973
  - 165-Presbyterian University Hospital--Comprehensive Chronic Renal Care System for Western Pennsylvania, 1973
  - 166-American Heart Association, Southwestern Pennsylvania--Southwest Pennsylvania Hypertension Control Program for Greene-Fayette Counties, 1973
  - 167-Butler County Health and Welfare--Planning for an Experimental Health Care Delivery System, 1973
  - 168-Eastern Allegheny County Hospital Corporation--Quality Assurance Programs for selected Allegheny County Hospitals, 1973
  - 169-Terrace Village Health Center--Evaluation of Medical Care Quality, 1973
  - 170-University of Pittsburgh--Regional Radiation Therapy Project, 1973
  - 171-Magee-Womens Hospital--Western Pennsylvania Neonatal Project, 1973
  - 172-Centralized Hospital Service of Westmoreland County--Quality Assurance Program, 1973
  - 173-University of Pittsburgh--Evaluation of Ambulatory Care of Patients with Hypertension, 1973
  - 174-Allegheny County Health Department--Maternity and Infant Care Application, 1973
  - 175-Ohio Valley General Hospital--Construction and Renovation, 1973
  - 176-Shadyside Hospital--Parking Garage Expansion, 1973
  - 177-Community Health Association of Western Pennsylvania--Continuation Application, 1973
  - 178-Monsour Hospital--Primary Care Module, 1973
  - 179-Old People's Home Western Pennsylvania, West Virginia--Eighty Bed Addition, 1973
  - 180-Lawrence County Commissioners, Laurence County Home--Phase I Renovation, 1974
  - 181-McMurray Hills Manor--Expansion of Facility to Include Addition of Forty-eight I.C.F. Beds, 1973
  - 182-University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Western Psychiatric Institute and Clinic--Continuation Grant, 1973
  - 183-Home Health Care, Inc.--Home Health Care Proposal, 1973
  - 184-Community Medical Center of Northeast Butler County--National Health Service Corps Proposal, 1973
  - 185-Albert Gallatin Medical Advisory Committee of Southwest Fayette County--National Health Service Corps Proposal, 1973
  - 186-Kiski Valley Medical Planning Committee--National Health Service Corps Proposal, 1973 (Box 101)
  - 187-not present
  - 188-Monsour Hospital--Hypertension Intervention Program, 1973
  - 189-Connellsville State General Hospital--Establishing a Physical Therapy and Rehabilitation Department, 1975
  - 190-not present
  - 191-not present
  - 192-Allegheny County Health Department-- Neighborhood Improvement Rodent Control Continuation Project, 1974
  - 193-Mt. View Christian Home--Expansion of Facility, 1975
  - 194-Divine Providence Hospital--Rectilinear Scanner, 1974
  - 195-Divine Providence Hospital--Electro-Encephalograph Machine, 1974
  - 196-Ladies of the Grand Army of the Republic Home--Renovation, 1974
  - 197-McGuire Memorial Home for the Mentally Retarded--Application for Reimbursement under the Medical Assistance Program, 1974
  - 198-Uniontown Hospital--Replacement of X-ray Equipment, 1974
  - 199-Uniontown Hospital--Purchase of a Coulter Chemistry II, 1974
  - 200-Uniontown Hospital--Improvements to ICU Department, 1974
  - 201-Uniontown Hospital--Rewiring Nurses Residence and Nursing School, 1974
  - 202-Shadyside Hospital--Renovations to the Pavilion and South Building, 1974
  - 203-not present
  - 204-Latrobe Area Hospital, Community Mental Health Center--Federal Staffing Grant Continuation, 1974
  - 205-Bethlen Home--Adding Thirty ICF Beds, 1975
  - 206-Saint Francis College--Physician's Assistance Program, 1974
  - 207-Irene Stacy Community Mental Health Center--Continuation Federal Staffing Grant, 1974
  - 208-Montefiore Hospital--Integral Parking Garage, 1975
  - 209-Jack Reese Nursing and Rehabilitation Service--Expansion Proposal, 1974
  - 210-Forbes Health System--First, Second, Third and Fourth Annual Reports, 1975
  - 211-North Hills Passavant Hospital--Professional Office Building, 1974
  - 212-Braddock General Hospital--Inpatient Psychiatric Unit, 1974
  - 213-Allegheny General Hospital--Chronic Renal Dialysis Therapy Unit, 1974
  - 214-Homewood-Brushton Neighborhood Health Center--Drug Rehabilitation Center, 1974
  - 215-St. Clair Memorial Hospital--Replacement of Equipment, 1974 (Box 102)
  - 216-South Hills Health System-Homestead Division--Repair of Boiler House, Replacement of Three Boilers and Improvements to the Steam Generating Distribution System, 1974
  - 217-Family Planning Council of Western Pennsylvania--Application for Continuation Grant, 1974
  - 218-University of Pittsburgh--Adult Nurse Practitioner: The Education of Nurses in Adult Ambulatory Care, 1974
  - 219-Beaver County Heart Association--Lipid Screening Project, 1974
  - 220-Magee Women's Hospital--Western Pennsylvania Regional Neonatal Program, 1974
  - 221-Presbyterian University Hospital--Expansion of Renal Therapy Resources in Western Pennsylvania, 1974
  - 222-John J. Kane Hospital--Additions and Modifications to Existing Electrical Emergency Systems, 1974
  - 223-Westmoreland Manor--Additions and Expansions, 1975
  - 224-Allegheny General Hospital--Incremental Child Health Program, 1974
  - 225-St. Francis Hospital--Renal Disease Program, 1974
  - 226-University of Pittsburgh, Clinical Medicine--Regional Program for the Delivery of Health Care in Butler County, 1974
  - 227-Butler County Health and Welfare--Planning for the Delivery of Health Care in Butler County, 1974
  - 228-Centralized Hospital Service of Westmoreland County--Quality Assurance Program, 1974
  - 229-not present
  - 230-Sewickley Valley Hospital Home Health Agency--Beaver Valley Home Health Audit Project, 1974
  - 231-Eastern Allegheny County Hospital Corporation--Quality Assurance Project, 1974
  - 232-Pennsylvania Physical Therapy Association--Pilot Project to Develop and Implement Physical Therapy Audit in Five Pittsburgh Hospitals, 1974
  - 233-not present
  - 234-Augustine's Italian Village--Construction of a Nursing Home in New Castle, 1974
  - 235-Monsour Hospital--Primary Care Module in Sewickley, 1974
  - 236-Allegheny County Health Department--Continuation Application for Immunization Project, 1974 (Box 103)
  - 237-Slippery Rock State College--Baccalaureate Program in Nursing, 1974
  - 238-Mahoning Shenango Area Health Education Network--Request for Continued Funding, 1974
  - 239-Western Pennsylvania Regional Medical Program--Core Continuation Application, 1974
  - 240-Home for Crippled Children--Remodeling Project, 1974
  - 241-Vocational Rehabilitation Center--Long Range Plan and Addition to Present Facility, 1974
  - 242-University of Pittsburgh, School of Social Work--Application to the VA for Assistance in the Education of Students in Health Service Planning, 1974
  - 243-John J. Kane Hospital--Life Safety Code, 1974
  - 244-not present
  - 245-Centralized Hospital Services--Health Information System for Westmoreland County, 1974
  - 246-Harmarville Rehabilitation Center--Planning for the Rehabilitation of Post-acute Care Cardiac Patients, 1974